Ready, set, go, we step over the goal line
isse nou se de fumikomu gourain
Still, we don't know anything at all
bokura wa nanimo nanimo mada shiranu
We look back as we pass the line, and it's already gone
issen koete furikaeruto mou nai
Still, we don't know anything at all
bokura wa nanimo nanimo mada shiranu
Fiercely, fiercely we move on
udatte udatte udatteku
Drenched in glistening sweat
kirameku ase ga koboreru no sa
There probably were a lot of things we didn't remember
oboetenai koto mo takusan atta darou
Everyone was just a silhouette
daremo kare mo shiruetto
Let's become adults,
daiji ni shitai mono motte otona ni naru nda
holding on to things we want to cherish
And let's keep on protecting them at all times
donna toki mo hanasazu ni mamori tsudzukeyou
Then someday...
soshitara itsu no hi ni ka
We'll be able to laugh at it all
nanimo kamo o waraerusa
Like the light and nimble dancing
hirari to hirari to matteru
Of leaves taking flight
konoha ga tonde yuku
The Three Questions
(木ノ葉丸)シカマルの兄ちゃん
何やってるんだ これ。
Big Brother Shikamaru,
what's going on?
(シカマル)ん？ ここで中忍選抜の
一次試験をやるから➡
Hmm?
The first round of the Chunin Exams
will be held here,
そのためのちょっとした改修だよ。
so we're just making
a few upgrades.
(ウドン)中忍試験
久しぶりにやるんだ。
The Chunin Exams!
It's been a while
since they last held them!
２年ぶりだな。
It's been two years...
だったら俺たちも
受けるんだな これ。
That means we get to participate!
(モエギ)私たち もう
中忍になれちゃうのね。
We can be chunin!
お前ら まだアカデミーの生徒だろ？
You guys are
still Academy students.
下忍ですらないのに
受けらんねえよ。
You're not even genin,
you can't participate.
(ウドン)残念なような
助かったような…。
That's kind of a disappointment,
but also a big relief...
そうか ナルトの兄ちゃん
帰ってくるんだな これ。
I see, so this means
Big Brother Naruto's coming back!
ん？ ナルト？
Huh? Naruto?
中忍試験 受けに来るんでしょ？
He's coming back to take
the Chunin Exams, right?
来ねえよ。
えっ。
He's not coming.
What?
ふぅ…。
どこで どう修業してるのか
消息不明のままだ。
Who knows where or how
he's training right now.
His whereabouts are still unknown.
中忍試験やることが➡
I don't know if he even
got the news
伝わってるのかどうかも
わかんねえ。
that we're holding
the Chunin Exams.
ナルトの兄ちゃん抜きで
やるってのか これ。
Does this mean
they're going to proceed
without Big Brother Naruto?
(シカマル)里もあいつの都合に
合わせちゃいらんねえからな。
It's not like the village can plan
things to fit his schedule.
(モエギ)ナルト兄ちゃん
落ちこぼれちゃうね。
Big Bro's going to be left behind.
(ウドン)リーダー失格だよ。
Our leader's going to
get disqualified!
(ユカタ)砂隠れの代表として
絶対に中忍になろうね。
We're representing the Hidden Sand,
so we have to become chunin, okay?
(マツリ)今から無駄に
張りきらないの。
It's too soon to get
all worked up.
(ミコシ)落ち着きたまえ ユカタ。
Calm down, Yukata.
(サジン)フッ…。
(ヒナタ)試験官の１人に
シカマル君がいるみたいだね。
Seems like Shikamaru
will be a proctor.
(シノ)そういうこともあるだろう。
That's not surprising.
なぜなら あいつは
すでに中忍なのだから。
It's because he's already a chunin.
(キバ)ばしっと決めて 俺たちも
さっさと中忍になっちまおうぜ。
Then let's buckle down and
get promoted to chunin too! Right?
な！
ワン！
(サクラ)よろしく。
Looking forward to
doing this with you!
(いの)頑張ろうね。
(チョウジ)うん。
- Let's kick some butt.
- Yeah!
(イズモ)はい。
この３人での受験ですね。
All right, so the three of you
are taking the exams, correct?
受け付けました。
You've been signed up.
今回は 志願書出させないような
仕掛けをやらないんですか？
There's no trick this time,
like preventing us from submitting
an application is there?
(コテツ)試験は
担当の試験官しだいですから。
The exam is up to
the proctor in charge.
はい ３人で引いてください。
Okay, pull lots.
３？
２？
Three?
Two?
１？
One?
札は戻して それぞれ引いた番号の
教室へ行ってください。
Return the lots and please proceed
to the classroom that you picked.
(チョウジ)不気味なまでに丁寧だね。
They're so polite,
it's almost creepy.
(サクラ)シカマルのしわざ？
Did Shikamaru plan this?
(いの)何 考えてんだか。
What is he thinking?
はい 次の方。
Next, please.
(イズモ)滝隠れからの受験者ですね。
You're the entrants from
Hidden Waterfall Village.
(フウ)フウっす。
(コテツ)はい 引いてください。
The name's Fuu.
All right, please pull a lot.
(リー)満を持したわけですから➡
We've waited so long for this,
中忍になりましょう。
so we have to make it
and become chunin!
ハッ ハッ ハッ ていや…。
(テンテン)あ～ もう うるさい。
You're so loud!
(ナルト)中忍選抜試験会場はここか？
ん？
Is this where the Chunin Exams
are being held?!
よっ 戻ってきてやったってばよ。
Hey! I'm back.
(リー)ナルト君。
ハッ。
Naruto!
ウソ ナルトなの？
(リー)本物ですか？
No way...
Is that you, Naruto?!
Are you real?
本物だってばよ。
I'm real!
(テンテン)何か あまり
変わってないわね。
You really haven't changed much.
え… そんなことはねえ！
Sure, I have! Want to see
the results of all my training?
修業の成果を見せてやるぜ。
は～！
おいろけの術。
Sexy Jutsu!
どうだってばよ
ほれほれ それそれ。
How's that?
Here! There!
相変わらずのバカだ。
He's as stupid as ever...
しかし これでこそナルト君ですよ。
And that's why Naruto is Naruto.
(ネジ)白眼！
Byakugan!
さあ 俺も試験受けるってばよ。
All right, I'm going to take part
in the Exams too.
(リー)ああ しかし
三人一組でなければ…。
But you need a team of three.
ああ 帰ってきたばかりで
誰もいないんだから➡
I just came home and
there's no one left,
特例ってことで
受けさせろってばよ。
so I'll just ask them to
make an exception.
てっ…。
Huh?!
あぁ…。
何のマネだ。
What's the big idea?
(モエギ)木ノ葉丸ちゃんを
責めないで。
Don't get mad at Konohamaru!
大丈夫？ 木ノ葉丸ちゃん。
Are you all right, Konohamaru?
みんな ナルト兄ちゃんのためなんだ。
It's all for Big Brother Naruto.
(ネジ)ナルトの？
Naruto?
ナルト兄ちゃん
試験を受けられないから。
Because Big Brother
can't take the exams.
中忍になれなくなっちゃうから。
It's because he won't be able
to be a chunin.
代わりに受けようとしたのか。
So you tried to take it
for him instead...
替え玉受験ね。
A stand-in test taker...
(ネジ)
お前たちが心配することはない。
You don't need to worry
about him.
ナルトは 中忍とか
そういう枠にとらわれず➡
Naruto's is someone who'll
keep striving to become Hokage
without getting hung up on
the details like becoming a chunin.
火影を目指すやつだ。
そうですとも。
He's right.
戻ってきたら みんなで
笑顔で迎えましょう。
And when he returns,
we'll welcome him with a big smile.
わかったよ。
I got it.
(コテツ)では 次の方。
Next in line.
１。
３。
One.
Three...
２。
(コテツ)では それを置いて➡
Two...
Okay, leave the lots and
go to your assigned rooms.
各々の教室へ。
１番は この先の教室に➡
Room One is
the classroom up ahead.
２番と３番は 階段を上がって。
Rooms Two and Three
are up the stairs.
えっ？ 分かれちゃうの？
別々になるんですか？
Huh? We're being separated?
We're on our own?
俺が１番だ。
I'm in Room One.
あっ！
ネジ兄さん…。
Oh!
Big Brother Neji!
(コムギ)なんでチームがバラバラなんだ？
Why were we separated
from our teams?
(シビレ)わかんねえよ。
I have no idea.
(シラ)あれ？ んっ ふっ！
Huh?
(シラ)開かない…。
It won't open.
どういうことでしょう!?
試験官は来ないの？
I wonder what's happening?
Isn't the proctor coming?
何か企んでるわね。
They're planning something...
ヘッ！ 何でもこいだ！
Heh, bring it on!
(コムギ)紙が置いてあるぞ。
There's a stack of papers here.
うかつに触らないほうがいいぜ。
[スピーカ](シカマル)あ～ ゴホンッ！
You shouldn't go around
carelessly touching things...
Uh... Ahem!
中忍選抜第一試験
試験官の 奈良シカマルだ。
I am Shikamaru Nara,
the proctor for the first round
of the Chunin Exams.
受験生は 教卓上の試験用紙を
１枚とって➡
Participants, take one sheet from
the stack on the teacher's desk,
好きな席につくように。
then take any seat.
一次はやっぱり 筆記試験か。
Round One is a written test,
after all.
よかった いつもどおりだ。
Oh good, it's the same as usual.
[スピーカ](シカマル)あ～ みんな
席についたか？
Is everyone seated?
[スピーカ]めんどくせえから
さっさといくぞ。
This is a drag,
so let's get right to it.
[モニタ]めんどくせえって何だよ！
This is a drag for him?
[モニタ]こっちは真剣なんだ！
We're serious about this!
運がいいぜ お前ら。
今年は 俺がルールで。
You guys are lucky.
I'm in charge this year.
言えてるかも。
(ヒナタ)どうして？
He might be right.
Why?
理不尽なことはしないと思うよ。
He won't do anything unreasonable.
一次は筆記だ。
問題を見るように。
Round One is a written test.
Read the questions carefully.
(コムギ)問題は３つ。
Three questions...
[スピーカ]３問ある問題の配点は
上からそれぞれ➡
The three questions are worth,
from the top:
30点 40点 50点だ。
30 points, 40 points,
and 50 points.
全部解くと 120点…。
A perfect score is 120 points?
う～ん 100点じゃないのか。
Not 100?
[スピーカ]各人 その３問の中から
１問だけ解答しろ。
Each of you will answer
just one of three questions.
合否は チームの合計点で判断する。
Your team's total points
will determine pass-fail.
まず ３人の合計点が
100を超えたチームは 失格とする。
If your team total exceeds 100,
the team is disqualified.
何だよそれ!?
(ミコシ)つまり こういうことですか。
That's crazy!
Then, for example...
３人で 30 30 50で
110点。
If the three have...
30, 30, 50 for 110 points...
30 40 40で 110点。
30, 40, 40 for 110 points...
40 40 40で120点。
or 40, 40, 40 for 120 points...
[モニタ](ミコシ)そういう合計点だと
失格になるのですね？
These totals will
disqualify them, right?
次に 残ったチームで平均点を出し➡
Then we'll take the average
of the teams who remain...
得点が平均点未満のチームは失格。
and teams who score below
the average will be disqualified.
[スピーカ]平均点以上を合格とする。
Those over the average will pass.
平均点？
３人の合計点のか…。
An average score?
Of the teams' totals...?
待ってくれ。
いったい どうやって…。
Just a minute.
How are we supposed to...?!
試験開始だ。
The exam starts now.
どの問題を…
解いたらいいんだ…。
Which question should I solve?
全然わかりません！ この問題！
I don't understand
this question at all!
ただ問題を解けばいい
という問題じゃないのね。
The question isn't just about
solving the questions...
この問題は。
余計にこんがらがること
言わないで！
Please don't say things that
will confuse me even more!
The three questions aren't that hard.
《問題は ３問とも
そう難しくない。
よほどのバカでもないかぎり
50点の問題も解けるだろう》
Unless you're really dumb,
anyone can solve
the 50-point question too.
((ナメんじゃねえ！
俺は逃げねえぞ！
Don't underestimate me!
I won't run! I'll take the exam!
受けてやる！ もし一生
下忍のままだって➡
I don't care if I get stuck as
a genin for the rest of my life,
(意地でも火影になってやるから
別にいいってばよ！))
because I'll be Hokage someday,
no matter what!
フッ…。
《ネジ : そういえばいたな
よほどのバカが。
Come to think of it...
there was a guy
who was really that dumb...
あいつは １問も解けずに
一次試験を突破したんだった。
He couldn't solve a single question
in the first-round exam,
but he passed.
つまり 前回と同様に➡
Which means...
They're not testing
our problem-solving skills.
問題解答能力が
問われているわけではない》
It's the same as the last time!
《さて… 100点になる
組み合わせは 30 30 40。
Now then...
100 points is either...
30, 30 and 40...
あるいは 50 50 ０か…》
Or 50, 50 and 0.
(テマリ)この一次試験の意図は何だ？
What's the whole point
of this first-round exam?
問題は チームの他の２人が➡
The point of it is to think about
how your other two
team members will score.
どの点を取るかを考えることだ。
あるいは 他の２人に
どの点を取らせるかをな。
Or rather, how to make your two
team members get a certain score.
となると この試験は➡
That gives an advantage to teams
who know jutsu to contact each other.
離れた仲間とコンタクトが取れる
術者がいたら有利じゃないのか？
それならそれで
別にかまわねえよ。
If that's the case, that's fine.
そういう技術のあるチームが
100点を取るだけのことだ。
All it means is that those teams
that have those skills will get 100 points.
他のチームも何とかしろ
ということか。
And the rest have to suck it up
and figure something out, huh?
たしか 前回の一次も
そんな問題だったな。
The first-round test in
the last Chunin Exams
was just like this, wasn't it?
問題は点数じゃない。
The point count isn't what's important.
中忍選抜試験ってのは➡
The Chunin Exams shine
the light on who is captain material.
部隊長を見いだす試験だ。
強さを見るだけなら
俺は中忍になってねえよ。
If the point was to test strength,
I wouldn't be a chunin.
そのとおりだな。
フォローなしかよ！
I guess so.
What? No snide comeback?
《シノ : 密閉されている》
It's been sealed off.
ネジ兄さん？
Big Brother Neji?
Double paned windows, huh...
二重窓か。
急きょ防音工事をしたようだな。
They made sure that
we couldn't contact our teammates.
Should you be moving around like that?
そんな勝手に
動いたりしていいの？
We were told a few rules,
but no one's cautioned us yet
禁止事項はいくつか言われたが➡
こうして話していても
注意はされない。
for talking like this.
NO UNAUTHORIZED FIGHTING
I see...
そうか。
つまり カンニングすら
問題視されていない。
So, they don't care if
we cheat or not.
That's right...
そういえば前回の一次は
カンニングのテストだったわ。
Last time, the first exam
was all about cheating.
(コムギ)開かないな。
It won't open...
Leave it to Shikamaru...
This is a difficult problem.
さすがシカマル君。
この問題 難しい。
If you can contact your teammates,
you gain an advantage for this exam...
この試験 別にされた
他の２人の仲間と➡
コンタクトを取れれば有利だが➡
But nobody on my team
uses such ninjutsu.
俺の班に
そんな忍術使いはいない。
シノ君は 何か手があるのかな。
I wonder if Shino has any ideas...
The only thing left is to try to guess
which question my teammate will solve.
なければ 仲間が どの問題を
解くのかを推測するしかない。
(ネジ)１ ２ ３に
分かれたからといって➡
If we choose the number
we each picked...
the point total will be over 100.
その順番で問題を解けば
100点をオーバーする。
(コムギ)100点オーバーは即失格だ。
Going over 100 points
means immediate disqualification.
We have to avoid that at all cost.
それだけは避けておかないと。
If one of us scores zero points,
we'll avoid going over 100, right?
誰か１人でも０点を取れば➡
100点オーバーによる失格はないよな。
だが 他の２人が
50点の問題を解く保証もない。
But there's no guarantee
that the other two will each answer
the 50-point question.
(サクラ)それに合計点が低ければ➡
And if the point total is too low,
there's a good possibility of
being dropped for a low average.
平均点未満で失格になる可能性が
高くなるわ。
If all of us solve the 30-point question
and get 90 points,
全員30点の問題を解いて
合計90点じゃ➡
we'll lose to the team
that has 100.
100点を取ったチームには
勝てないってことか。
If many teams score 100 points,
100点を取るチームが多ければ➡
and raise the average score,
teams with 90 points will be disqualified.
平均点が上がって
90点のチームでも失格になるのよ。
う～ん 抜け道を作るっていうのは
無理そうね。
I guess finding
a loophole seems impossible.
The choices are 30, 30, 40
or 0, 50, 50 to score 100 points.
(サクラ)100点になる組み合わせは➡
30 30 40か ０ 50 50。
So the question is...
チームの中で 誰が
どの問題を解くのかを考える。
figuring out which question
each team member will solve.
それが問題よ。
How should I know what
questions Ino and Sakura will pick?
いのとサクラが
どの問題を解くかなんて➡
わからないよ。
What would Shino and Kiba do?
シノ君とキバ君 どうするだろう。
向こうもそうやって➡
Those two are probably wondering
the same thing right now.
こちらのことを
考えているだろうな。
Got it! I finally figured it out!
わかった！
やっとわかりましたよ。
Huh? You did?
えっ わかったの？
はい！
Yes!
I solved the 50-point question!
50点の問題 答えがわかりました！
あっ そう。
Oh... I see.
I'm not going to show you.
見せませんからね。
見ないわよ。
I won't look.
I don't have to look.
見なくていいわよ。
ふぅ～。
Who are you?
《何者だ。
蟲使いには見えないが》
You don't seem to be
an Insect User, but...
I hate to say this,
but if Naruto were here,
(サクラ)愚痴になっちゃうけど
この一次➡
this first-round exam
would be easy.
ナルトがいてくれたら
簡単だったのに。
Huh? Why?
(テンテン)えっ どうして？
I mean, he'd score zero for sure.
だって あいつ
絶対０点取るもの。
(キバ)いくらナルトだって➡
I think even Naruto could
solve this 30-point question.
この30点の問題は
解けるんじゃねえのか？
Definitely not.
いや 絶対無理。
あぁ… さすがナルトか。
Leave it to Naruto...
It would be much simpler if Lee
on our team was as obviously dumb.
うちのチームのリーも➡
そこまではっきりバカだったら
楽だったのに。
Umm... Excuse me.
あの ちょっとすみません。
Yes?
何？
結局➡
Can you tell me just what
we're supposed to do
この一次試験って
どうすればいいんですか？
for this first-round exam?
それをみんな悩んでるのよ？
That's what we're trying
to figure out!
You too, huh?
ですよね。
These questions are
really hard, aren't they?
この問題 全部難しいですよね。
あっ まあね。
Well... yeah.
Wouldn't you think
the safest thing to do
(ヒナタ)安全策を考えたら➡
is for each of us to choose
the 30-point question?
全員が30点を解けばいいと
考えないかな？
Didn't he say something
about the average score too?
(チョウジ)でも平均点が
どうとか言ってなかった？
I see... We have to score 100 points,
no matter what.
そうか どうしても
100点を取るしかないんだね。
I can't even figure out
how to get 100 points.
(コムギ)どうやったら
100点取れるか➡
全然わからないのに。
(ネジ)時間だけが過ぎていく。
And time keeps on ticking away...
《修業は積んできた。
I've trained hard... I'll try it.
やってみよう。
First, I have to sense those two.
まずは２人を感知する》
Hey, you two, please listen...
《２人とも 聞いてほしいっす》
(クン)ん。
Is that you, Fuu?
《フウか よし》
All right.
What're you up to?
あんた それ何のマネ？
《アジサイ : 仲間に》
My teammates...
Sensory Jutsu!
《スイレン : 感知の術》
Four...? I see...
《４？
あっ そうか》
わからない。
I don't get it.
Choji...
《いの : チョウジ》
えっ!?
Huh?!
I'll solve the 40-point question,
so Choji, you do the 30-pointer.
《私が40点を解くから➡
チョウジは30点を解いて》
Oh, okay. Okay!
ああ うん うん！
I'll get Sakura to do the 30-pointer too.
《いの : サクラにも
30点を解かせるから》
Hey, Gennai! Inaho!
お～い 源内 イナホ！
Can you hear me?!
聞こえるか～？
Tanzo, Minoji!
(シビレ)あっ タンゾウ ミノジ！
It's me!
俺だ～！
– It's me!
– Hey! It's me!
うう 何のマネだよ。
– What are you trying to do?
– Can you hear me?
At this rate,
no one's voice will be heard.
これじゃあ
誰の声も届かないのに。
(リー)あっ。
Do you hear something?
何か聞こえませんか？
Is someone yelling?
誰かが何かを叫んでるのか。
That's right!
(源内)そうか
他の部屋に声が伝われば。
If they can hear me
on the other side...!
Hey!
(ミノジ)お～い！
聞こえるか～！
Can you hear me?!
何か聞こえるな。
I can hear something.
Someone's yelling.
(テンテン)誰か叫んでる。
A lot of people are yelling.
大勢の声よ。
(イナホ)そうか。
I see.
Hey!
(タンゾウ)お～い！
(イナホ)コムギ 源内。
Komugi, Gennai!
やっほ～ やっほ～。
Yahoo!
Shouldn't we stop them?!
止めなくていいのか？
If I stop them,
this exam would be meaningless.
俺が止めたら試験の意味がない。
Now then,
who's doing to do what?
《さて 誰がどうする？》
I'll do the 50-point question!
俺は50点 解くぞ！
I'll do the 40-point one!
俺は40点だぞ！
It's so noisy.
ああ うるさい
聞こえるわけないでしょうに。
Who can hear over all this?
There's shouting in
the other classes too.
他の教室でも叫んでる。
Everyone's voices are
blending together
みんなの声が混じりあって➡
and nothing can
be communicated.
これじゃ何も伝わらない。
Nothing can be communicated, huh?
《何も伝わらないか。
Just watch...
フッ 見てろよ。
Sand Letters!
砂文字》
"I'll do the 40-point question."
《ムジン : 俺は40点を解く》
(ミジン)あっ。
It's Sajin!
《サジンか 俺たちに
30点を解けというわけか》
He wants us to do the 30-pointer.
With that we'll total 100 points.
《これで俺たちは 合計100点だ。
Those fools...
フッ バカどもが》
ヒナタ様。
Lady Hinata...
Let's continue your lesson here.
稽古の続きを今 ここで。
What are you saying,
Big Brother Neji?
ネジ兄さん 何を？
There's something I want to try.
試してみたいことがあります。
わかりました。
All right.
Perform the Eight Trigrams:
Air Palm...
八卦空掌を… 全力で。
with all your might.
うわ～！
– Eight Trigrams: Air Palm!
(２人)八卦空掌！
うっ。
何だ!?
W-What the—?!
(コムギ)お おい。
Hey...
You guys...
お前ら。
What the hell are you guys doing?!
(サジン)いったい何のマネだ!?
Showing you the answer
to the question.
お前たちに
この問題の解き方を教えてやる。
nando tatakitsukerarete mo
No matter how many times I get beat down
akiramerareru wake nado wanaku genten kaiki
I can't give up, so I go back to my basics
genjitsu to wa baibai shite
I wish we could say bye-bye to this reality
mukashi mitai ni waiwai shitai keredo
And have fun like we used to
sou mo ikanai nara kirihiraite mirya ii
But it doesn't work that way,
so let's carve out our own paths
nokori wazuka no shouki torimodoshite
I'll make you get back the little sanity you have left
me no mae no tobira kojiakete miseru
And then tear down the door in front of you
itsudemo sou nanda
That's the way it is
wasuregachina koto ga
The things you tend to forget
nani yori mo taisetsuna koto datte
Are the things that are the most important
nani ga machiukete iyou to kamawanai
I don't care what lies ahead
ame nimo makezu yami o terasu
The rain won't stop me from lighting up the darkness
kono kyoujin na kokoro ga areba
As long as I have this strong spirit
kono toki kono basho ni tsudoishi nakamatachi
Friends who gather at this time, at this place
mawari tsudzukeru sekai nanbitotari
The world keeps spinning, No one can stop it
tomo tomeru koto wa dekinai yo
What's the answer
that you prepared?
This question wouldn't exist
if I wasn't the proctor.
That's why there is no point
in me answering that question.
皆様 お変わりございませんか？
What are you quibbling about?
美空ひばりです。
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"One Worthy As A Leader"
では最後まで
ごゆっくりお楽しみください。
All right,
Let's see what Neji's going to do.
『木曜８時のコンサート
名曲！ にっぽんの歌』。
今回は 歌謡界を代表する➡